So when I was speaking about virtue of
the mind,
um something I had thought of um
bringing up is why is it that um this is
to say that virtue is a necessary
precondition like purification of virtue
not just some amount of virtue but
purification of virtue is a precondition
for purification of chitta which is a
precondition for purification of you.
for purification of you.
Why is it that you can't just take a
random person off of the street and then
tell them to abandon the five hindrances
and purify their
chitta just by telling them to to do
exactly what the Buddha said in the in
the in the sutas just to abandon greed
and aversion in regard to the world um
abandon covetousness.
Why wouldn't they be able to do that?
because acting in certain ways whether
they recognize it or not is accepting
that version. Mhm. But but what what
will happen if let's say at that moment
they're not acting in any in any uh un
wholesome ways like for that moment
factually they're kind of they're not
breaking any precepts cuz they're
sitting down in a room not doing
anything. So they're kind of in
seclusion at that moment. So why why
would they fail?
Do they lack a degree of self
transparency? Um yeah, but that that
would be like a very broad like that
wouldn't necessarily tell you like what
what do I do then? What can I fix how
can I fix that? They still be looking at
objects in at stuff and things arise and
blaming them as well or trying to solve
problem by replacing Mhm. getting more
or less. Why would that why why is that
a problem first of all? Uh well because
the problem is not with the things that
arise. Uhhuh. And why that would be is
because but what if what if they just decide
but what if what if they just decide
like okay now I heard that that the
objects are not a problem so I won't
replace them anymore. Well, yeah, you
might have the thought, but if you have
been cultivating the your view, your
attitude, let's say, towards your
experience of getting rid of the stuff that bothers
of getting rid of the stuff that bothers
me and getting the stuff that satisfies
me is what you call
beneficial. You can't decide not to have
that attitude. You have to undo it. And
it's going to take a while. And as soon
as you
stop fueling it, you will well quite
quick quickly realize the way that
everything that you were doing before
was secondary. Yeah. Yeah. And also how
dependent on it you are. M well yeah
that's the point because it's it's
uh cuz you know you might think like
okay so obviously the the focusing on
objects is wrong like replacing the one
thing with another that's that's with
basic self transparency you realize
that's only going to be a temporary
solution but um it goes much deeper than
just not having heard that right
information. It's because even if you
get the right information of, oh, I
shouldn't be replacing things, I should
be enduring them on the right level,
quote unquote, that entire project is
going to still be rooted to some extent
in the fact that you don't want to
endure the pressure because if you if
you allow the pressure to come up, you
will do the things that you're used to
doing unaccountably. So you won't be
able to not act out of sensuality and
get up and go out leave in seclusion if
if a real sensual thought were to arise.
Um so because you're just not used to
not the precepts that's the point of
precept. It's not a not
um like just keeping this external
behavior independently of what's going
on in your mind. It's like the whole
point of the precept is to train you so
that even if these things arise, you
don't have to. If you if you spend most
of your day
um in a state of trance, not even
allowing these things to come up, then
even if you keep your virtue for 20
years, you haven't trained yourself
because the whole point was to to um
like when the mind was aware of these
things, training it not to go for them
automatically. And so only when that's
in place, you will be able to um train
the wild like the elephant as the as as
we put it. Um you will be able to cuz
see it's like it's like the
elephant hasn't even you haven't even
tied it
down. So then like oh it's not. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. As I was going to say, do
you even see your mind if it's if it
isn't in relation to taking the virtue
seriously first? Yeah. Like the virtue
basically like the purification of
virtue is precisely on the on the level
of not acting out of not acting out unh
wholesomely. Even by body, speech and
mind in rel mind
mono which is thought in relation to
that chitta which sits behind that and
which is putting the pressure there. So
if those precepts are not adhered to
from the start, you're not even going to
see that mind pressuring you and you and
you will still hold the
view which is quite common that like the
whole practice is supposed to prevent
the pressure from coming up because
that's that's that's exactly the same
thing the same goal because of which you
act out of sensuality, act out of
aversion and push because you don't want
to have the pressure there. So anything
you do with within that framework will
carry that same goal with it. I don't
want to to hear my mind complaining. So
I would just either give it what it
wants. Yeah. Or or just put it to sleep.
Yeah. And so in the beginning there's
going to be a conflict in a sense
between you wanted to keep the precepts
and your mind
putting pressure on you wanting to go
the other way. And then there can be a
natural inclination saying look I do not
want to have that inner conflict. So
either you need to be stronger and tain
the mind or you're going to give in to
the mind in order to dissolve the
conflict. Now if you give in in the long
run you'll make it worse. So you have no
choice but to endure it so that you
become stronger then that's pressuring
chitta which is always behind you. Yeah.
So, it's uh it's it's
essential to be self honest about the
fact that if you just look at something else
that if you just look at something else
and completely forget about that
pressure, you're not dealing with the
problem. Even if temporarily you don't
feel the pressure anymore because the
the the
the situation of suffering was pressure
being present. So, anything that you
develop apart from that setup is completely
apart from that setup is completely
relevant to yes to to like what the
problem actually was. Yeah. It's like
yeah I can I can I don't know I
can I can run when uh when it's not
uphill. If it's uphill I can't do it
anymore. Mhm. And like the whole point
is the difficulty was you couldn't run
uphill. So you can be the fastest person
in the world running
downhill. It doesn't matter. Mhm. And
that's that's the that's the whole um
uh idea of meditation today. It's it's
uh based on that
um just just developing this huge piling
up this huge set of skills quote
unquote in the domain that's completely
separate from the problem that you were
met with in which is the relationship
between you and your mind and and and
and who is now basically in charge of
who so you just you just you're able to
do all this stuff and and have all this
peace and
because the things that provoke the mind
are not there anymore.
And oh actually the the Buddha gave that
simile like the the the point is was to
take that elephant and tame it. Yeah. So
that it would become a battle elephant.
So that even when the the it would hear
the the drums and people throwing spears
at it and see the like hear the see the
the enemy's armies marching towards it
that it wouldn't run away. Um that was
the whole purpose of of taking that
elephant out of the forest. Yeah. So, um
if if now like the elephant is is is
tamed because nothing's going on, then
um you you lost sight of what actually
mattered at some point clearly because
the the
uh that's what pressures are. It's are
it's things that are if the elephant is
the cheetah, then the mind, then that's
what these uh pressures are. It's like
those those
um the enemy trying to to attack and and
get the elephant to run away or or um
whatever just just not do what it's what
you expect and put up with it. Yeah. Be
be moved past basically.
So you miss and you mis ascribe that um
like factual benefit of like the
elephant not moving or say you you
actually go higher up this hill and you
can see further but it's because you've
just been kind of running around and you
happen to climb higher and can see
further and you think it's because
you've been running around and
developing all these skills that you can
see further. Yeah. And actually it was
just you endured and
developed. Well the thing is no even
then the things that you would get to
see on the basis of wrong samadi on the
on the basis of wrong samadi on the
basis of samadi that's that's like
about blindfolding the elephant and not
letting it perceive anything.
There is knowledge that can arise out of
that as would say out of wrong samadi
arises wrong knowledge but the knowledge
will be on exactly the same level as the
whole samadei and exactly on the same
level as a whole wrong view of
management. So all of those insights
that you would see coming out of this of
of that kind of practice of ignoring
which is what meditation is about for
most people would be about like yeah you
would hear oh everything is as we was
discussing in that previous talk like oh
everything is empty it doesn't really
exist or it's all constantly changing or
you see the the kind of um whatever mind
flickering out of whatever whatever
infinite array views you might come up
with just to to justify yourself or or
to make yourself feel at ease with that
pressure because you don't want to put
up with it. You want to to some extent
kind of dampen it. You want to decrease
it because uh you have to convince the
elephant. Oh, no. Actually, that's not
the enemy's army. Those are our friends.
Just just be quiet. Don't move. Um
because you know that if the if you just
let the elephant accept the actual
reality without imposing um these extra
layers of rationalization over it, then
it's it's it's it's going to run. So um
in other words, it hasn't been properly
trained. Yeah. Exactly.
And then the right knowledge would come
out of that. Like when the mind isn't
moved by anything like as the sutra
would say um even if violent or or kind
of aggressive sights, sounds, smells,
taste, touches, not just physical
sensations as people would think like I
can endure the whatever
um not sleeping, not eating, not
breathing as the Buddha was was doing.
No, it's like sights, sounds, smells,
thoughts, even enduring those things on
that much more personal level.
Um that's that's uh that's what attained
mind is able to do and then um on the
basis of those things you would be able
to actually recognize the knowledge that
matters like four noble truths which is
none of this was the problem. None of
this pressure was the problem. Uh cuz
now you're able to
actually like for as long as you're not
able to endure it. you won't even be
able to direct yourself or to or to
rightly consider the idea that it wasn't
the problem because the mind will
keep constantly kind of putting you on
the spot to like no no you have to deal
with it you have to deal with it only
when it stops and it doesn't care about
the pressure anymore see that doesn't
automatically mean that you will have uh
right knowledge because some people
develop their minds in the sutas without
getting the right view. But if you have
the right information and you direct
yourself, you you direct your mind to
that right information as they would say
of the four noble truths um then you
will get to see it because now it's now
the the obstructions that
were like your
investment in wanting to assume that
things are otherwise just so that you
can deal with the pressure now that's
gone. So there's nothing preventing you
from seeing the obvious nature of like
oh no it's actually it wasn't the sight
sounds smells taste touches thoughts
phenomena nothing was just my craving in
regard to this whole thing and then
nothing can bother you again once you
see that so
Is there is there a place
for relaxing in the sense that if you're so
relaxing in the sense that if you're so
used to trying to manage the situation
um whether through just explaining to
yourself like no the pressure is not the
problem like everything that you've
discussed and learned
No, you don't
even need to do that. You're just going
to endure them.
Stop mudd muddling water. Y um in a way
it kind of I don't know would it be fair
to Yeah. would it does relieve the
burden but actually the jitter becomes
much more agitated at the same time. So
there is a maybe on one level there's
sort of a reaxing but it's more
uncomfortable. Yeah. Yeah. That's that's
exactly what I was going to say. So the
problem is when you have the expectation
that the
relaxation, the release, the the
um giving up is supposed to be pleasant
immediately. The sutas actually say
quite the
opposite especially if you haven't been
developed in virtue. Um the Buddha even
said like that which the noble ones
regard as pleasant ordinary people
regard as unleasent and vice versa. like
the sessation of
um the sessation of of everything, like
the sensation of your sense of self,
sensation of appropriation, sensation of
any sense of control that you might have
over things. for somebody who's still
dependent on that sense of control and
still actively exerts it and and asserts
it through their
actions. Um, this is going to be like
like jumping in a in a pool of cold
water just when you're cold. Um, uh,
when you're warm, sorry. So, um, it's
going to be the complete opposite
direction of everything that you're used
to. So, but from a certain sense you
realize the the the burden the
burdenlessness of pronunciation of
giving things up of non- craving is
something that you need to learn to
value before it can be pleasant. That's
why some some sutas would say that um
like once you've gone forth the
difficult thing is to be content.
Um so and and uh the others would say
like the neutral feeling when you don't
understand it it's going to be
unpleasant when you understand it it's
going to be peaceful. So neutral feeling
is basically that direction of
uh giving up of engagements, giving up
of concerns, giving up of of
involvements. But when the mind is still
with the momentum of passion, aversion
and delusion,
um yeah, it's like when you break a car,
it's like, you know, it's there's that
momentum and and
um it's it's uh probably yeah, it's
going to start trying to convince you to
to keep
going. So that's when you need to hold
it back. As again going back to the
simulant, that is the actual purpose of
the force of the batanas. It's not for
you to just just ignore the whole thing
and and enter a different dimension.
It's when the mind is is pressuring you
to to um continue with that momentum of
concerns and passions and involvements
even if it's not inside of the precepts.
You tie it down and you refuse
to lose the context of the body,
feelings, mind and phenomena. So these
are ways for you to be able to endure
the pressure, not ways for you to be
able to replace
it. That's why the Buddha would say um
yeah, it compared the the foranas to
like the post to which you would tie
down the elephant until it comes down.
So far from being uh an immediately
pleasant endeavor, it's it's actually
like a like an arduous training, which
is why he had to keep encouraging monks
to be diligent and not not
uh not a relaxer effort because if it
were a matter of just like um sunshine
and and vacation from day one, then you
wouldn't need an encouragement to do it. So that same
same
pain like it's not a it's not a
torturous pain like when you're kind of
it's not the same pain as
as I don't know um getting your limbs
chopped off or something. It's it's um
the pain of of just having a certain
pressure there and uh not giving it to
no matter how much how strongly it
arises. That same
pressure if when you understand it
rightly is where the peace comes from
because you highlight the aspect of well
this is not mine. See, that's the that's
the that's another thing like the as we
were saying why why the Buddha wouldn't
be teaching he wouldn't
start his his training to some random
person by saying oh nothing is there's
no self
um everything is impermanence by telling
them the formal truths first he would
always begin by saying first the
clansman hears the teaching and gains
faith he goes forth having gone forth he
establishes himself in virtue, then the
sense restraint, then all these other
things. And at like at the last step of
his whole training, then he gets to
understand um the four truths, impermanence, the
um the four truths, impermanence, the
three characteristics, but whichever way
you want to approach it, five
aggregates, because if he were to start
with that, like telling yourself, oh, this is
that, like telling yourself, oh, this is
not mine as people usually do or there
is no self. You're doing that because
you want to get rid of the pressure. In
other words, because you're taking it as
mine, because you you still insist in in
in controlling it, that's why you're
telling yourself these
things. On the other hand, when you've
actually developed yourself these
prerequisites, then this is not mine is your way of
then this is not mine is your way of
enduring the pressure, not your way of
running away from it.
And that is
pleasant because like
when when you when you
um I don't know
hear about something
happening somewhere else. You could have
been there, some catastrophe happening.
you could have been
there, but you realize that you you
weren't then like with the natural thing
you would feel is relief. So, it's the
same thing that in here like everything
that happens internally, quote unquote,
you're not there with it. So, it's like
hearing about floods and and disasters,
but then perpetually realizing that, you
know, it's you're
elsewhere. Now, doesn't mean that you're
unaware of it. doesn't mean that I don't
mean that you uh disappear into a
different dimension. Um obviously the
five aggregates are still there and
there's no outside of it but
um that sense of personal connection
like as a Buddha as as a Buddha would
say whatever feeling he feels whether
pleasant unpleasant or neutral he feels
it detached or disconnected.
So, it's not that you don't feel it,
it's that it's felt as disconnected.
Yeah, it did. It doesn't bother you.
Yeah. But see again you can take that on
an abstract level of a view before you
have developed yourself and still your
conception of like oh it doesn't bother
me would still imply some degree of
management. In order to really
understand for yourself what it means
not to be bothered. You have to develop
the mind first and then see like on that
proper level of pressure being arisen
and not being moved not as a matter of
choice because for as long as there's
pressure like the pressure is affecting
you and it's it's it's moving you. Your
choice to try not to be moved would be a
way of being moved. There's no way you
can escape that. um like as a matter of
choice only by developing as the Sutzu
would say the aggregate of virtue the
proper behavior beforehand to the point
where it doesn't even take effort for
you to maintain and it is and it's there
on its own as the aggregates are
um then it's like you would be able to
to um see what it is see what it means
not to be affected on the right level
without you having to try not not to be
affected. You recognize, oh, actually,
as long as I don't cross this line,
which actually takes effort, but I
didn't see it because I was used to
going over that line um as as a
beginningless habit. Um, if I don't
cross that line, there's nothing that
can affect. You don't even see that
management as Ashley Bism. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Actually, it's
it's a it's um it's a load. It's like a
like I think I've said it before, it's
like um Stockholm syndrome. It's like
something that you know it's actually
painful, but um because you're so used to it even
but um because you're so used to it even
when you get the chance to free yourself
from it, which is like perpetually
there, you don't want it because it's
it's it's feels more comfortable to keep
doing what you're used to. like the the
immediate safety of just gratifying that
desire for pleasure or gratifying that
aversion against pain and trying to get
rid of it. That feels kind of
um yeah like it feels like a like a
guaranteed um immediate reward. Whereas this is
um immediate reward. Whereas this is
like you're kind of open
to full
uncertainty of of like I can't
um I'm not going to I'm not going to
control this anymore. Um but it's a
completely different type
of ease or peace. It's it's uh like yeah
like like you can compare the the piece
of having your house or
whatever always in the perfect
temperature, the perfect humidity level,
no wind, no insects,
um whatever running
water and then you know all of that is
perpetually subject to all sorts of
things that can undermine it, you know,
the price of things. I don't know, the
water system breaks down, you have to
repair it. And now compare that with the piece
it. And now compare that with the piece
of living on the street, not caring
about whether it's hot, cold,
um warm, um humid, dry,
uh and you realize, oh, that's there's
basically even from that mundane
perspective, that other type of peace is
much more difficult to take away because
literally like it it basically doesn't
depend on anything. So it's the same
with your own mind like the wrong type
of peace is is when you depend on your
own aggregates on your own senses on
your own internal situation being a
certain way and
um everything again even the the the the
right things that the Buddha taught like
not self and so on you would if you
aren't if you're not developed in virtue
you will be using them still to manage
that internal internal environment to
keep the house at the perfect
temperature that you prefer. Whereas it
has to come first through you giving up
that comfort of management to begin with
and literally going out into the
homeless life internally at least like
you know not not um trying to manage
your own internal home quote because of
but for as long as you do you will not
be able to understand it is not mine.
Yeah. And then the real homelessness is
described as seeing the fire because
that's not yours. Oh yeah, right. I
think there was
a So that's why it says whether it's um
past, present, future, inferior or
sublime, uh coarse or subtle, all form is equally
uh coarse or subtle, all form is equally
seen as This is not mine. I am not this.
This is not myself. So rather rather
than starting from again the standard
attitude of management which is like I
first get the form I want and then I
tell myself that it's not mine when it's
like comfortable and easy. Um no it's
the other way around. You need to take
on the uncert uncertainty that any form
might arise, any feeling might arise,
any perception might arise.
because you're not acting out of your
gratuitous sense of control anymore. So
factually anything might happen and
that's how you would understand the true
uncertainty the aggregates which would
then free you
from any suffering that would come on
account of them but at not for free not
without the price of giving up the
satisfaction of control.
And then the fear would also be gone
because now it doesn't matter what the
do. Yeah. It's no longer your concern.
Then you realize it the fear wasn't same
as with all the other defundists. The
fear wasn't because of the external
things that like I didn't cultivate this
kind of manly attitude of bravery or
of manly attitude of bravery or
something. That's always going to be a
way of just managing the aggregates such
that they don't become a certain way
when you perceive whatever. Whereas that
that's not taking you beyond fear.
That's that's that's like same as when
um you look at like a certain food and
you try to convince yourself that it's
not tasty as if the lust was the fact
that the food was tasty. No, no, the
lust is when food is tasty, you are l
lustful towards it. So that's what you
have to train yourself in regard to the
same as we said before. You have to
climb the hill like you have to run when
it's uphill. So it's when the fear is
there, when the pressure is there,
freeing yourself from that, from any
need to act out of that, from any need
to manage that and run away from that.
That's the true going beyond fear. Not
like just cuz Yeah. How many things are
there in the world that you could be
afraid of? Infinite. Yes. So you would
never be able to just
um overcome fear by going through the
specific things and toughening up until
you can bear all of them. Same with
sensuality. Same with the version. You
cannot reach meta like the boundless
compassion that the Buddha talked about
by just spreading love towards each
individual person or group hoping that
they don't become your enemy so that you
then feel at ease. Because see it's it's
it's um again how many beings exist?
Mhm. How many groups of being exist
exist that you're not even aware of. So
the fact that you say may all beings be
happy. Well you don't know what all is.
Mhm. So through that attitude you will never
So through that attitude you will never
be able to include everything.
Instead you need to take it on the level
of it doesn't matter how any being makes
me feel internally. Mhm. Same as with
the fear. It doesn't matter what any
external thing arises in these
aggregates because you dwell
disconnected from the feeling. Yeah. I
will not I will not maintain the
assumption of ownership in regard to it.
So that's why somebody who gives up
appropriation of the five arrogates
would have automatically developed meta
even if they never heard about that
word. Yeah. And that is why we can also
perhaps reformulate saying that the
right toughening up would be as you said
in the beginning to start with the
virtue. Yeah. Of course. Yeah. Yeah.
uh if you if you're not keeping the
precepts but you're
um I think we said that before but but
you're uh putting up with all sorts of
insane physical challenges that's that's
not the right type of development
because I mean just think about it how
many people are there in the world who
can do difficult things on that physical
level compared to people who are
celibate by choice
forever. Yeah. So, um it's it's
it's even if it seems like you know when
people would say the monk's life is just
just bunch of bunch of good for nothing
just just passing their time
there staring at the wall. uh you
realize there's a reason why people
don't do it because there's plenty of
people in the world who um who just want
to to get easy food, easy gardens,
um easy medicine and they don't become.
So,